Joel Martin Halpern collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 2: Southeast Asian materials, 1957-2000
  - Subseries 1: Manuscript materials, 1957-1987, Dates in this series usually refer to publication dates; the collection contains many photocopies of publications, with some originals.
    - Joel Martin Halpern and Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern: Published texts, 1964-1987
      - Halpern, Joel, and Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern. Laos and America: a Retrospective View. South Atlantic Quarterly, vol. 63, no. 2, Spring 1964, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 18/181)
      - Hofner, James A., Joel Martin Halpern, and Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern. River Road through Laos: Reflections of the Mekong. Amherst: International Area Studies Programs, University of Massachusetts: 76 pages, 1983, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 18/182)
      - A Far World Comes Near: the Kingdom of Laos and Laotian American: an Exhibition of Laotian Arts and Culture. Amherst: Augusta Savage Gallery, University of Massachusetts: Apr. 1-Apr.17, 1987, publication prepared by Joel Martin Halpern and featuring the Laos photographs of Joel Martin Halpern and Sam Pettengill's photos of Laos in Western Massachusetts: 16 pages, 1987, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 18/183)
  - Subseries 2: Sound recordings, 1957-1958
    - Lao Boun celebration, Luang Prabang, Laos, 1957, AFC 1998/001: SR007; 1 reel-to-reel tape (7 inch)
    - Translated Lao children's essays, 1957, AFC 1998/001: SR008; 1 reel-to-reel tape (5 inch)
      Collected in Luang Prabang, Laos in 1957; translated in Los Angeles, California in 1968.
    - Translated Lao children's essays, 1957, AFC 1998/001: SR009; 1 reel-to-reel tape (5 inch)
    - Translated Lao children's essays, 1957, AFC 1998/001: SR010; 1 reel-to-reel tape (5 inch)
    - Translated Lao essays, 1957, AFC 1998/001: SR011; 1 reel-to-reel tape (5 inch)
    - Traditional Laotian orchestra taped over the Firestone Program, collected in Luang Prabang, Laos, 1957, AFC 1998/001: SR048; 1 reel-to-reel tape (7 inch)
    - Transcriptions in Lao, AFC 1998/001: SR012; 1 reel-to-reel tape (5 inch); See above
    - Smiles and Tears, 1958, AFC 1998/001: SR013; 1 reel-to-reel tape (5 inch)
      Lao autobiography made in Los Angeles, California.
    - Interview of Kahm Sinh (U.S. Information Service in Laos), 1958, AFC 1998/001: SR014; 1 reel-to-reel tape (5 inch)
      Record in Los Angeles, California.
    - Interview of Kahm Sinh, Los Angeles, CA, AFC 1998/001: SR015; 1 reel-to-reel tape (5 inch)
    - Interview of Kahm Sinh, Los Angeles, CA, AFC 1998/001: SR016; 1 reel-to-reel tape (5 inch)
    - Smiles and Tears, 1958, AFC 1998/001: SR017; 1 reel-to-reel tape (5 inch)
    - Khamvong Insixiengmai: Thinking About the Old Village Traditional Lao Music, AFC 1998/001: SR046; 1 audiocassette (90 minutes)
  - Subseries 3: Graphic materials, 1957-2000
    - Photocopies of photographs of Laos, 1957, June 3, 2000, 588 photocopied slide images; 1 letter (Box-folder 20/184)
      Captioned printouts of slide images, with a letter from Joel Halpern offering digital copies to the American Folklife Center.
  - Subseries 4: Moving images, 1957
    - Royal Processions, Mekong River Life, 1957 Luang Prabang, 1957, AFC 1998/001: MV03; Joel Martin Halpern; AFC 1998/001: VT003; 1 videocassette (120 minutes)
      Note on media: "Laos Tape Copy"
- Series 3: Inuit materials, 1952-2000
  - Subseries 1: Manuscript materials, 1952-2000, Dates in this series usually refer to publication dates; the collection contains many photocopies of publications, with some originals.
    - Joel Martin Halpern: Published texts, 1952-1989
      - Halpern, Joel Martin. Use of Minerals by the Copper Eskimo. Rocks and Minerals, January-February 1952, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/185)
      - Halpern, Joel Martin (ed.). Perspectives on Inuit Culture: A Five College Symposium and Art Exhibit. April 4-14, 1988: Proceedings and Catalog. Amherst: Dept. of Anthropology, University of Massachusetts: 36 pages, 1989, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/186)
    - Publications by other authors categorized by language, 1973-2000
      - English
        - Nuna Parr: Sculpture: 14 pages, 1985, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/187)
        - Gallery Indigena: 'Mother,'' 'Father and Sons,' 'Brothers:' 3 pamphlets, 1987, 1989, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/188)
        - The Sculpture of Henry Evaluardjuk: 16 pages, 1987, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/189)
        - The Way We Live: Sculptures by Levi Alasuak from Akluivik: 18 pages, 1988, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/190)
        - Center for Arctic Cultural Research Seventh Annual Report; Center for Arctic Cultural Research Ninth Annual Report, 1989-1990, 1991-1992, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/191)
        - Our Home and Native Land; A Film Resource Guide for Aboriginal Canadians: 34 pages, 1989, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/192)
        - Waddingtons Important Sale of Inuit Arts: 96 pages, 1990, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/193)
        - 1991 Cape Dorset Annual Graphics Collection: 19 pages, 1991, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/194)
        - A Celebration: Inuit Art 2000: 16 pages, 2000, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/195)
        - Coppermine: Sculpture: 13 pages, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/196)
        - Davie Atchealak: Sculpture: 11 pages, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/197)
        - The Far North. Museum of Fine Arts, Boston: 14 pages, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/198)
        - Inuit: The Eskimo word for himself: brochure, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/199)
        - Kania Etungat: Sculpture: 12 pages, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/200)
      - English and French
        - Canadian Inuit Sculpture, English / French: 36 pages, 1988, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/201)
        - La Fédération des Coopératives du Nouveau-Québec; Fine Arts and Crafts from Nouveau Québec. English / French: 9 pages, 1988, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/202)
        - Shamans and Spirits: Myths and Medical Symbolism in Eskimo Art: 32 pages, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/203)
      - English and Inuktitut
        - Sikkaurk, Nick. More Stories. (both English and Inuit versions): 37 pages, 1973, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/204)
        - Ajurnangimmat Magazine. (Text in both English and Inuit): 48 pages, 1983, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/205)
        - Owingaya, David K. Arctic Survival Book. (English / Inuit): 107 pages, 1986, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/206)
      - French
        - Espaces Inuit: exposition de dessins et sculptures inuit: 36 pages, 1991, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 21/207)
  - Subseries 2: Sound recordings, 1988
    - Inuit Artists; Jimmy Ayola, April 10, 1998, AFC 1998/001: SR033; 1 audiocassette (90 minutes); See also Box-Folder 21/186
      Recorded at Perspectives on Inuit Culture: A Five College Symposium and Art Exhibit, April 4-14, 1988, at University of Massachusetts, Amherst, Massachusetts.
    - Debbie Gordon (Inuit Broadcasting Corporation), April 11, 1998, AFC 1998/001: SR034; 1 audiocassette (90 minutes); See also Box-Folder 21/186
    - Titus Alloulou; Ernie Coverford, April 12, 1998, AFC 1998/001: SR035; 1 audiocassette (90 minutes); See also Box-Folder 21/186
    - David Owingayak (Inuit Cultural Institute, Arviat, Eskimo Point, Northwest Territories), April 14, 1998, AFC 1998/001: SR036; 1 audiocassette (90 minutes); See also Box-Folders 21/186 and 21/206
    - David Owingayak (Inuit Cultural Institute, Arviat, Eskimo Point, Northwest Territories), April 16, 1998, AFC 1998/001: SR037; 1 audiocassette (90 minutes)
    - David Owingayak (Inuit Cultural Institute, Arviat, Eskimo Point, Northwest Territories), April 16, 1998, AFC 1998/001: SR038; 1 audiocassette (90 minutes)
    - Side A: Inuit artist; Side B: Ayola and Jimmy, April 10, 1998, AFC 1998/001: SR039; 1 audiocassette (90 minutes); See also Box-Folder 21/186
    - Interview of Igloolik girls, October 24, 1988, AFC 1998/001: SR040; 1 audiocassette (90 minutes)
  - Subseries 3: Moving images, 1988
    - Discussion of Inuit culture, April 1988, AFC 1998/001: MV07; AFC 1998/001: VT007; 1 videocassette (120 minutes)
      With David Owingayak (Inuit Cultural Institute, Arviat, Eskimo Point, Northwest Territories), Laird Christie (Professor of Anthropology, Wilfrid Laurier University, Waterloo, Ontario) and Joel Martin Halpern. Recorded at Perspectives on Inuit Culture: A Five College Symposium and Art Exhibit, April 4-14, 1988, at University of Massachusetts, Amherst, Massachusetts.
- Series 4: Miscellaneous materials, 1943-1996
  - Subseries 1: Manuscript materials, 1943-1996, Dates in this series usually refer to publication dates; the collection contains many photocopies of publications, with some originals.
    - Joel Martin Halpern: Published texts, 1951-1996
      - Frobisher's False El Dorado. Rocks and Minerals: 261-2, May-June 1951, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 23/208)
      - Thomas Jefferson and the Geological Sciences. Rocks and Minerals, 601-2, November-December 1951, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 23/209)
      - Halpern, Carl with Joel Martin Halpern. Origins and Early Jobs. Bronx County Historical Society Journal, vol. 23, no. 2: 51-69 (note: Carl Halpern was the father of Joel Martin Halpern), Fall 1986, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 23/210)
      - Halpern, Carl with Joel Martin Halpern. Beginning a Career. Bronx County Historical Society Journal, vol. 27, no. 1, Spring 1990:1-24, 1990, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 23/211)
      - Halpern, Joel Martin, and T.L. Christie. Time: a Tripartite Sociotemporal Model. Dimensions of Time and Life, edited by Fraser, J.T. and M.P. Soulsby. Madison, Connecticut: International Universities Press: 187-98, 1996, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 23/212)
    - Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern: Unpublished texts, 1971
      - Where Has Modal Gone: 5 pages, 1971, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 23/213)
    - Publications by other authors categorized by language, 1943-1995
      - English
        - Herzog, George Foreword. (English) ix-xiv; Bartók, Béla Preface. (English), xv-xvi; Bartók, Béla Morphology: 72-83, 1943, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 23/214)
        - Hymes, Dell H. The Ethnography of Speaking. Anthropology and Human Behavior: 13-53, 1962, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 23/215)
        - Kiparsky, Paul and Carol Kiparsky. Fact: 26 pages, 1968, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 23/216)
        - Russo, Joseph, and Bennett Simon. Homeric Psychology and the Oral Epic Tradition. Journal of the History of Ideas 29: 483-98, 1968, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 23/217)
        - Stankiewicz, Edward Milestone of Yiddish Philology. (English): 368-71, 1969, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 23/218)
        - Cresswell, Robert. Lineage Endogamy Among Maronite Mountaineers. Nicosia: Mediterranean Social Anthropological and Sociological Conference, 7-12 September; Timetable. Cyprus: University of Paris, Social Research Centre, 1960, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 23/219)
        - Ahmajian, Adrian. On Deriving Cleft Sentences from Pseudo-Cleft Sentences: 149-68, 1970, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/220)
        - Bauman, Richard. An Ethnographic Framework for the Investigation of Communicative Behaviors: 334-40, 1971, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/221)
        - Yngve, Victor H. Human Linguistics and Face-to Face Interaction: 26 pages, 1973, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/222)
        - Kashubian Folklore in America. University of Virginia: American Contributions to the Seventh International Congress of Slavists: 419-37; Perkowski, Jan L. The Awakening of an Epic Poet. Proceedings from Pacific Northwest Conference on Foreign Languages: 226-28; correspondence from Perkowski to Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern included, 1973, 1972, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/223)
        - Newmeyer, Frederick J. Linguistic Theory and Linguistic Practice: the Class Nature of Hypocrisy: 15 pages, 1973, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/224)
        - Herzfeld, Michael. 'The Siege of Rhodes' and the Ethnography of Greek Oral Tradition. Harvard University: 414-40, 1973, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/225)
        - Andriolo, Karin R. A Structural Analysis of Genealogy and Worldview in the Old Testament. American Anthropologist, Vol 75 No 5, October 1973: 1657-69, 1973, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/226)
        - Andriolo, Alexander Eliot. The Greek Island that Blew Apart. Travel & Leisure, (English) July 1974: 32-5, 54-7, 1974, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/227)
        - Oral Literature at Harvard Since 1856. Harvard University History of the Parry-Lord Yugoslav Oral History Collection: 35 pages, 1974, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/228)
        - Foley, John Miles. Acknowledgments page from The Ritual Nature of Traditional Oral Poetry: Metrics, Music, and Matter in the Anglo-Saxon, Homeric Greek, and Serbo-Croatian Poetries: iv-vi, 1974, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/229)
        - Lex, Barbara W. Altered States of Consciousness in Northern Iroquoian Ritual: 276-300, 1976, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/230)
        - Ong, Walter J., S.J. From Mimesis to Irony: The Distancing of Voice. The Bulletin of The Midwest Modern Language Association, Vol. 9, No 1-2, Spring/Fall 1976: 24 pages, 1976, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/231)
        - Simon, Bennet. Hysteria: the Greek Disease. Psychoanalytic Study of Society, vol. VIII: 80 pages, 1976, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/232)
        - Ong, Walter J., S.J. Milton' s Logical Epic and Evolving Consciousness: 295-305, 1976, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/233)
        - Lex, Barbara W. Physiological Aspects of Ritual Trance: 109-22, 1976, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/234)
        - Anthropology & Education Quarterly, Vol VIII, No 3, 1977, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/235)
        - Pop, Mihai. Cultural Frames and Reflections: Ritual, Drama, and Spectacle. Romania: 25 pages, 1977, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/236)
        - Pop, Mihai. Dilemmas of Focus in Linguistics: 12 pages, 1977, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/237)
        - Frank, Roslyn M. The Religious Role of the Woman in Basque Culture. Anglo-American Contributions to Basque Studies: Essays in Honor of Jon Bilbao: 53-60, 1977, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/238)
        - Foley, John M. Riddles 53, 54, and 55: An Archetypal Symphony in Three Movements: 29-31, 1977, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/239)
        - Folklore Women' s Communication: brochure, 1978, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/240)
        - Lex, Barbara. Neurological Bases of Revitalization Movements. Zygon, vol. 13, no. 4, December 1978: 276-312, 1978, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/241)
        - Agar, Michael H., and George M. Beschner, editors. Angel Dust: An Ethnographic Study of PCP Users. Lexington, Mass.: D.C. Heath Lexington Books. Reviewed by Barbara W. Lex.: 4 pages, 1979, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/242)
        - Lex, Barbara. The Neurobiology of Ritual Trance. The Spectrum of Ritual: A Biogenetic Structural Analysis: 117-51, 1979, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/243)
        - Women and Folklore Conference: brochure, 1979, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/244)
        - MacMarshall (editor). Beliefs, Behaviors, and Alcoholic Beverages: A Cross-Cultural Survey. (Reviewed by Barbara W. Lex.) Ann Arbor: Journal of Drug Issues, Vol. 10 No 3: 385-87, 1980, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/245)
        - Moerman, Daniel. Edible Symbols: The Effectiveness of Placebos: 15 pages, 1980, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/246)
        - Nellis, Muriel. The Female Fix. Reviewed by Barbara W. Lex: 3 pages, 1980, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/247)
        - Beckelman, Laurie and Sarah Brown. Getting High: The Inside Story. McLean Hospital: 17 pages, 1980, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 24/248)
        - Cloud, Ellen Fulcher. From Whence We Came: The History of the Original Ocracoke Names: 76 pages, 1995, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/249)
        - Books By and About Women in Folklore: brochure; Williams, Selma R., and Pamela J. Williams. Riding the Nightmare: brochure, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/250)
        - Chomsky, Noam. Conditions on Rules of Grammar. Current Issues in Linguistic Theory, Indiana University Press: 3-49, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/251)
        - Cloud, Ellen Fulcher. The Federal Census of Portsmouth Island NC 1790-1900. (area of Ocracoke) Live Oak Publications, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/252)
        - The Haymes Bibliography of Oral Theory. Harvard University: brochure, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/253)
        - Jackendoff, Ray, and Peter Culicover. A Reconsideration of Dative Movements or, Beating a Dead Horse Back to Life: 13 pages, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/254)
        - Fishman, Joshua A. The Sociology of Language: Yesterday, Today, and Tomorrow. Current Issues in Linguistic Theory. Indiana University Press: 51-75, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/255)
        - Stankiewicz, Edward. Sound and Sight in the 'Sonety Krymskie' of Adam Mickiwicz. Yale University: 495-503, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/256)
        - Creed, Robert P. Widsith' s Journey Through Germanic Tradition: 376-87, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/257)
      - French
        - L' Homme: Revue Française d' Anthropologie: 55 pages, 1964, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/258)
      - Italian
        - Maconi, Vittorio. Etonologia Sociale (translated title: Social Ethnography) Editrice Studium, Roma: 211 pages, 1953, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/259)
      - Multi-language articles
        - Translations, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 25/260)
  - Subseries 2: Moving images, 1992
    - The Ocracoke Brogue, AFC 1998/001: MV08; Ocracoke Preservation Society; AFC 1998/001: VT008; 1 videocassette (120 minutes); See also Box-Folders 25/249 and 25/252
      North Carolina Language and Life Project